Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association of the U.S.A. Records
Sophia Smith Collection
Pan Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association of the U.S.A. records
1938-2007
Pan Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association of the U.S.A.
MS 336
12 boxes (5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
International women's organization. The records of the Pan Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association of the U.S.A. consist of international conference proceedings, from the 10th, 11th, and 13th-15th conferences; correspondence; minutes of the executive board and other meetings; reports; constitution and by-laws; publications and printed material; and photographs of the national PPSEA taken between 1950-1985. The records also include two scrapbooks, newspaper clippings, and records from four local chapters including New York, Chicago, Toledo (OH), and Stockton (CA).
Historical Note
The Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association (PPSEAWA) was founded in Honolulu, Hawaii in 1930 with the intention to "strengthen the bonds of peace among Pacific peoples by promoting a better understanding and friendship among the women of all Pacific countries." The women organizers also sought to "promote co-operation...for the study and betterment of existing conditions" throughout the Pacific Rim. The Association initially conducted its work primarily through international meetings where delegates shared information and raised awareness about international women's issues.
PPSEAWA evolved to encompass an international umbrella organization and autonomous national associations, which had local chapters. Beginning in 1930, the national chapters of PPSEAWA, which include countries of the South Pacific and Pacific Islands, Southeast and East Asia as well as the United States, convened triennially for international conferences to share information and coordinate programming. The groups also kept in contact through newsletters.
The American section of the international membership organization-the Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association of the U.S.A. (PPSEAWA-USA), the entity that generated the records in the Sophia Smith Collection-has had chapters in cities that ranged from New York City to Stockton, California and Valdosta, Georgia. The Toledo, Ohio and New York City chapters became the most active U.S. chapters in the 1950s and 1960s, a time in which PPSEAWA was among a group of internationalist organizations promoting stronger alliances between the U.S. and Pacific Rim countries. In the early 1950s, PPSEAWA International established consultative status at the United Nations and UNESCO as a non-governmental organization. Although PPSEAWA was not oriented toward political advocacy, this network exerted an influence on and was shaped by liberal Cold War foreign policy. Declaring its "unique function" to bring together women "not as specialists or as feminists but as people interested in exchanging ideas and practical experiences," PPSEAWA-USA sponsored programs that brought together clubwomen activists with diplomats and cultural ambassadors. Events such as lectures and fashion shows were designed to foster personal interactions as well as intercultural appreciation. PPSEAWA leaders in the New York area provided hospitality services for visitors and emigrants to the U.S., and they participated in United Nations efforts.
PPSEAWA remains active. In the United States, it has been primarily an educational organization that promotes contact among women interested in Asian and Pacific issues. Notable members of PPSEAWA-USA have included Ella Stewart, the first licensed African-American woman pharmacist in the United States, Goodwill Ambassador to the Department of State, and president of the National Association of Colored Women; and social work educator Elmina Lucke. Internationally, chapters carry out community development and women's health programs while remaining closely involved with United Nations activities.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The PPSEAWA-USA Records consist of 5 linear feet of organizational materials, dating from 1938 to 2007. They include minutes and reports, correspondence, conference materials, newsletters, and scrapbooks.
The bulk of the records are dated from the 1950s to the 1960s. SERIES I. HISTORY AND ADMINISTRATION documents the administration of the national organization and provides some information regarding local chapters and international activities. It also contains scrapbooks (one of which is located in the OVERSIZE MATERIALS) that document international conferences and the group's history with photographs and memorabilia. SERIES II. CONFERENCES contains materials generated by PPSEAWA's international conferences. These materials cover a large span of the organization's history. SERIES III. PUBLICATIONS includes long-term runs of the international and American newsletters. The "Heritage Books" contained in this series detail the histories of PPSEAWA International and its member organizations.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into three series:
I. HISTORY AND ADMINISTRATION
II. CONFERENCES
III. PUBLICATIONS
This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
The Sophia Smith Collection owns copyright to PPSEAWA-USA's unpublished works. Permission must be obtained to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use." Copyright to materials authored by others may be owned by those individuals or their heirs or assigns. It is the responsibility of the researcher to identify and satisfy the holders of all copyrights. Permission to publish reproductions or quotations beyond "fair use" must also be obtained from the Sophia Smith Collection as owners of the physical property.
Additional Formats
This collection had been digitized and is available online (with database subscription). Also available on microfilm (Contact the SSC for more information).
The Pan-Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association of the U.S.A. began to donate its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1988.
Pan Pacific and Southeast Asia Women's Association; Asia, Southeastern--Women--History--Sources; Pacific Islanders; Islands of the Pacific--Women--History--Sources; Pan-Pacific relations--History--Sources; Women--Asia, Southeastern--Congresses; Women--Asia, Southeastern--History--Sources; Women--International cooperation--History--Sources; Women--Pacific Area--Congresses
Related materials can be found in the papers of PPSEAWA members Gladys M. Bradley, Elmina Lucke, and Josephine Schain, also housed in the Sophia Smith Collection. The Swarthmore College Peace Collection in Swarthmore, Pennsylvania holds a portion of the PPSEAWA-USA Records, documenting the years between the 1920s and 1940s.
- SERIES I. HISTORY AND ADMINISTRATION
  - Brochures, histories, and general publications 1939-94 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bylaws 1956-70 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Event programs and invitations 1957-79 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, financial materials, and reports
    - 1938-40 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - 1950-64 (Box 1, Folder 5-10)
    - 1965-85 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
  - Correspondence
    - To members, general 1939-58 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - A-R 1955-58 (Box 3, Folder 2-11)
    - S 1955-88 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - State, Department of 1956-58 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - T-Z 1954-59, [1968?] (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Chapter files
    - Australia-Japan 2004-06, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - New Zealand 1963-64, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Tonga n.d. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - United States
      - Hawaii 2003-08 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Toledo, Ohio 1963, 1999, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 5)
        [see also Correspondence, T]
  - Clippings 1928-92 (Box 5, Folder 6-8)
  - Scrapbooks
    [see also Oversize and Flat File]
    - Janet Fowler 1955-57 (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
    - "Modes and Mores of the Orient II" 1958 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - "Ten Years of PPSEAWA-USA 1957-67" (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - PPSEAWA international conference, Auckland, New Zealand 1972 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- SERIES II. CONFERENCES
  - PPSEAWA international and regional conferences
    - 1940-81 (Box 7, Folder 1-6)
    - 1984-94 (Box 8, Folder 1-6)
    - 1995-2004 (Box 9, Folder 1-6)
  - United Nations conferences: PPSEAWA reports and conference materials
    - General 1955-2004 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - UN Center Development 1969 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - World Youth Assembly 1970 (Box 10, Folder 4)
- SERIES III. PUBLICATIONS
  - Cookbook 1981 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Heritage books 1990-2007 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - PPSEAWA Bulletin/International Bulletin: newsletter 1959-2001 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - PPSEAWA -USA newsletter 1954-2006 (Box 11, Folder 4-6)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - PPSEAWA conference, Tonga 1964: commemorative stamps (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Fiji Community Education Training Centre: scrapbook 1986? (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Posters 1991-2007 (Map-case Flat file)
  - Memorabilia (Map-case Flat file)